A Finding Aid to the Kenworth Moffett Papers, circa 1959-1988, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Kenworth Moffett papers
circa 1959-1988
Archives of American Art
Moffett, Kenworth
AAA.moffkenw
Archival Resource Key
0.6 Linear feet
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Kenworth Moffett measure 0.6 linear feet and date from circa 1959 to 1988. The papers document Moffett's career as a critic and curator through correspondence, slides and photographs of works of art by artists who were subjects of Moffet's research, notes, teaching material from his time at Wellesley College, and unpublished papers written by colleagues and students.
Biographical / Historical
Kenworth Moffett (1934-2016) was an art critic, curator, and art museum director in Massachusetts and Fort Lauderdale, Florida.
Moffett studied art history at Columbia University and earned a PhD from Harvard University in 1968. A champion of Color Field painting, he wrote critical essays and reviews for major art periodicals including Artforum and Art International throughout the late 1960s to 1970s.
From 1968 to 1979, Moffett was a professor of art history at Wellesley College. In 1971, he was made founding curator of twentieth-century art at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, where he organized exhibitions of sculptor Anthony Caro and painters Jules Olitski, Barnet Newman, and Friedel Dzubas. He also curated the first museum exhibition of realist Albert York. In 1989, Moffett was appointed director of the Museum of Art Fort Lauderdale, where he remained until 1997. Moffett died in 2016.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Lucy Baker, former wife of Kenworth Moffett, 1993.
Art museum curators -- Massachusetts; Art museum directors -- Florida -- Fort Lauderdale; Art critics -- Massachusetts
- Kenworth Moffett papers, circa 1959-1988; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes correspondence, slides and photographs of works of art by artists who were subjects of Moffet's research, notes, teaching material from his time at Wellesley College, writings by students, an edition of the "Moffett's Artletter" newsletter, and an NEA grant application related to an exhibition, Abstract Sculpture Since 1945.
  - Correspondence, 1976-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Art Seminar Courses, Wellesley College, 1970-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Writings by Students, 1970-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Student Blue Books, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Abstract Sculpture Since 1945" Exhibition NEA Grant Application, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Moffett's Artletter", 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, Art, circa 1959-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Slides, Art, 1963-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Slides, Art, 1979-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1967-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)